Guide to the Ford Foundation records, US and International Affairs, Education and Culture Office Files FA1427
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, US and International Affairs, Education and Culture Office Files
1987-1995
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1427
4.56 Cubic Feet 12 document containers
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into three series:
1. Desk Files, 1992-1994
2. General Office Files, 1993-1995
3. Chronological Correspondence Files, 1987-1994
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, reports, desk files, and conference materials from the US and International Affairs Division, Education and Culture Program. The collection spans from 1992-1995.
Biographical / Historical
In the 1990s, the Ford Foundation's Education and Culture program worked to strengthen educational and cultural institutions by expanding opportunities for disadvantaged students, fostering appreciation of diversity in the arts, and encouraging effective teaching and scholarship in the social sciences, particularly in foreign area studies, African American studies, and women's and gender studies.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2017 and 2019 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accessions 2017:087 and 2019:012.
Ford Foundation
- Desk Files, 1992-1994; 1; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  - Choice: What Role in American Education?, October 1, 1992 Meeting (Economic Policy Institute), 1992 October (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Cynthia Enloe, Clark University, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Correspondence with/regarding Cynthia Enloe
  - Environment and Development Forum (Korten/Maughan), 1993 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Freedom of Expression" Meeting, 1993 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Future Programming (Alison Bernstein), 1993 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Princeton University (Alison Bernstein), 1992 July 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rand Corporation (Lyon), 1993 July 12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Women's Program Forum (Campbell/Zwerling), 1993 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Women's Studies Request for Proposal (ARB/JP), 1994 November (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "World Wide Funds" (Alison Bernstein), 1992 August 10 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - New York Donors Group - Meeting at Ford Foundation - Phelps-Stokes Fund Pamphlets, 1993 August 10 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- General Office Files, 1993-1995; 2; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  - Program Officer Position, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 30-31)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted - Executive Search - Open in 2033
  - K-12 Search (Background Material), 1993 (Box 4, Folder 32-34)
  - General Files A-E, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Correspondence Alison Bernstein and Education and Culture staff from organizations: Association for Community Based Education, American Association of Museums, Black Student Fund, Binney and Smith, Inc., Center for Educational Innovation, Connecticut College, The College Board, Center for Educational Innovation, City University of New York, Citizens for Equity in Education Funding Political Action Committee, Council on Foundations 46th Annual Conference, Columbia College, Center for Educational Innovation, Convenant Foundation, National Conference on State Legislatures, the Ellington Fund, Empowering America's Cities Forum
    Arrangement
    Arranged alphabetically by organization
  - General Files F-Mc, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Correspondence Alison Bernstein and Education and Culture staff from organizations: Five College Program in Peace and World Security Studies, Fund for New York City Public Education, High 5 Tickets to the Arts, Harvard/Outward Bound Project in Experience-Based Education, Jeffrey Herbst, Institute for Educational Leadership, Inc., Institute for EastWing Studies, Institute for Women's Policy Research, Institute of International Education, Joyce Foundation, Learning Research and Development Center, Mary Baldwin College, Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, Midwestern Higher Education Commission, John Morning Design, Mississippi University for Women, Ms. Foundation for Women, St. Mary's University, and Phyllis McClure
  - General Files N-W, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Correspondence Alison Bernstein and Education and Culture staff from organizations: New York University, New York Public Library, National Summit on World-Class Education for All America's Children, National Humanities Center, National Center for Restructuring Education, Schools, and Teaching, New American Schools Development Corporation, Carolyn Pate, Recruiting New Teachers, Inc., Rutgers University Foundation, Rockefeller Foundation, Souhegan High School, Southern Education Foundation, Some Corporate and Foundation Relations Officers SCAFRO '95, Spelman College, Social Science Research Council, Tin-Swe Thant, University of Vermont, Vassar College, The Washington Center, Women's Research and Education Institute, and Woodrow Wilson National Fellowship Foundation
- Chronological Correspondence Files, 1987-1994; 3; 4.18 Cubic Feet 11 letter document boxes
  This series contains correspondence files of staff within the Education and Culture Office at the Ford Foundation. The series includes correspondence files of Peter W. Stanley, Edward J. Meade, Jr., Alison R. Bernstein, Sheila Biddle, Barbara R. Hatton, Ruth R. Mayleas, Barbara S. Nelson, Nancy L. McCarthy, Michele Cole, Steven Zwerling, Edgar Beckham, and Christine Vincent.
  - Education and Culture Chron Volume I - Sheila Biddle Correspondence, 1993 September-December (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Education and Culture Chron Volume I - L. Steven Zwerling Correspondence, 1993 September-December (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Education and Culture Chron Volume I - Alison Bernstein Correspondence, 1993 September-December (Box 2, Folder 18, Box 3, Folder 19)
    Responses to potential grantees and requests for information
  - Education and Culture Chron Volume II - Edgar F. Beckham, 1993 September-December (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Education and Culture Chron Volume II - Administrative Unit, 1993 September-December (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Education and Culture Chron Volume II - Christine Vincent, 1993 September-December (Box 3, Folder 22-25)
  - Alison R. Bernstein - Alpha/Chrons - A-B, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Alison R. Bernstein - Alpha/Chrons - C-G, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Alison R. Bernstein - Alpha/Chrons - H-P, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Alison R. Bernstein - Alpha/Chrons - Q-Z, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Staff Chronological Correspondence, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 30-31)
    Includes correspondence files of Peter W. Stanley, Edward J. Meade, Jr., Alison R. Bernstein, Sheila Biddle, Barbara R. Hatton, Ruth R. Mayleas, Barbara S. Nelson, Nancy L. McCarthy, Michele Cole
  - Staff Chronological Correspondence, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 32-34, Box 6, Folder 35-41, Box 7, Folder 42-47, Box 8, Folder 48-52, Box 9, Folder 53-57)
  - Staff Chronological Correspondence, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 58, Box 10, Folder 59-62, Box 11, Folder 63-66, Box 12, Folder 67-70)